Isabel Neto (University of Lisbon)

PhD Candidate

Isabel.canico.neto@gmail.com; https://isabelcaniconeto.github.io/site/

About me

A PhD student in the Computer Science and Engineering, IST - Technical Institute from the University of Lisbon and researcher in GAIPS –"Research Group on AI for People and the Society, and "Visualization and Intelligent Multimodal Interfaces Group" at INESC-ID. With a focus on social agents for inclusion in schools. Supervised by Prof. Ana Paiva and Prof. Hugo Nicolau.

The main research interests are in the fields of **Social Robotics**, **Children Education**, **Accessibility**, **Children**, **and Human-Robot Interaction**.

With 20 + years of experience senior leadership, design, business, people and change in the **Telecommunications Industry**, in Vodafone, embraced several technical and management areas in Digital, Customer Operations and IT. Collaborated with many talented people having a long experience in a customer-centric approach, leading design thinking methods to build and develop personalized and ethical experience in digital channels & assisted channels, such as social media platforms, chat& chatbots, mobile applications and web sites for self-care, eCommerce and campaigns. **Passionate about people**, I had managed teams for over 16 years

Nowadays, left the industry and invested in postgraduate study to deepen knowledge and skills in **Artificial Intelligence applied to children**, moved by knowledge enrichment and to help create and provide a better life for the disabled (visual, motor, autism and nervous system disorders) and older people. Passionately believe that virtual agents, robots, and an early diagnosis will be a crucial enabler to provide more autonomy for them.

Currently, running two main areas of research (1) **Promote inclusion between children** with multi-visual abilities in an inclusive school, using social robots (2) explore the **pervasive computing potential** in the **rehabilitation process** after a Cerebral Vascular Accident (CVA) working with a local hospital for children.

Publications

Neto, I., Paiva, A. and Nicolau, H. 2021. Community Based Robot Design for Classrooms with Mixed Visual Abilities Children. CHI '21: Proceedings of the 2021 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (2021).

Neto, I., Nicolau, H. and Paiva, A. 2021. Fostering Inclusive Activities in Mixed-visual Abilities Classrooms using Social Robots. Companion of the 2021 ACM/IEEE International Conference on Human-Robot Interaction (HRI '21 Companion), March 2021, Boulder, CO, USA2021, Boulder, CO, USA (2021), 8–10.

Neto, I., Johal, W., Couto, M., Nicolau, H., Paiva, A. and Guneysu, A. 2020. Using Tabletop Robots to promote Inclusive Classroom Experiences. IDC 2020- Proceedings of the 2020 ACM Conference on Interaction Design and Children (2020).

Neto, I. 2020. Using Social Robots to Create Inclusive Classroom Experiences for Children with Mixed Visual Abilities. ASSETS 2020 - 22nd International ACM SIGACCESS Conference on Computers and Accessibility - DC (2020), 1–5.

Education

PhD Student in Computer Science and Engineering (2019 - x) - Lisbon Tech Institute, University of Lisbon **Computer Science and Engineering Degree** - Lisbon Tech Institute, University of Lisbon

Research Experience

Research Assistant (2019 - x) - Lisbon University - IST

In GAIPS –"Research Group on AI for People and the Society, and "Visualization and Intelligent Multimodal Interfaces Group", researching in robot's interaction with visually impaired children.

Assisting in, project ARCADE Augmenting Rehabilitation Centres with Context-Aware Digital Environments, focused on rehabilitation after Cerebral Vascular Accident (CVA), in Synthetic Characters Group and Visualization and Intelligent Multimodal Interfaces Group (INESC-ID).

Teacher Assistant

Lisbon Tech Institute, University of Lisbon (Mar 2021 -x)

Industry Footprint

Vodafone Portugal (January 1996 – January 2020)

DIGITAL Manager & Senior Product Owner (2018-2020)

- Accountabilities: Responsible for the **Digital Channel** roadmap, engagement, strategy, budget control, delivery web and mobile development, and UX&UI design, for eCommerce, customer care, search and assisted help (such as chat, chatbot & social networks).
- Main achievements: *App My Vodafone* engagement, which in 3 years ramp up from 150k to more than **11Millon visits per month**, customer satisfaction focus (**NPS ~35**), **Digital tools implementation** (Adobe Audience, Target and analytics, replay sessions, internal search engine).

Head of Digital in Customer Operations (2014 - 2018)

- Accountabilities: Digital (UX&UI, self-care channels& digital tools analytics and search) and Billing Area (finishing and digital Invoice) & social networks support
- Main achievements: Selfcare app and web roadmap (increase 5x of use of digital channels, 80% of customer use digital bill, 95% of all customer contacts made by these channels), Sentiment analysis, Agile Product Owner and Digital Tools Integration.

IT Delivery Manager Online & Finance Projects (2011- 2014)

- Accountabilities: Vendor management (outsourcing AD&M), Project and Program Management, Delivery manager for Strategic Projects (Online and Finance Area), Demand management and Budget control. Responsible for BI and Online Domain in Vodafone Portugal.
- Main achievements: Digital projects implementation (eShop, self-care web and single sign-on), Advisor for Oracle (Customer Advisory Board) for WebCenter platform, Speaker in Oracle Open World Conference (2014), Finance projects implementation (HP FMS Fraud, HP Data Retention, Callidus commissions system, Tallyman debt management)

IT Delivery Manager – Technical and Finance Projects (2008 - 2011)

- Accountabilities: Vendor management, IT Program management for Fixed Line Offer, Demand management and Budget control. Responsible for BI Domain in Vodafone Portugal.
- Main achievements: Responsible for Fixed-line implementation and launch (FTTh launch, TV implementation and Shared Fixed Network with Optimus), and Finance Projects (RAID revenue assurance).

IT Manager - Analysis Team & Project Management (2006 - 2008)

- Accountabilities: Vendor management (AD&M), Program Management, Demand Management and Budget control
- Main achievements: Responsible for Fixed-line ADSL implementation and launch, and managing the Business Analysis Team for BI, SAP, Commissions and Logistics Area,

<u>IT Manager for ERP projects and support (1996 - 2006)</u> • Main achievements: Launch of Bad debt projects, workflows and Document Management (Filenet)

<u>IT Analyst and Project Manager (1996 - 2001)</u> Main achievements: Launch of SAP R3 and Portability Project MGT, Abap development and Team Leader of a development team